Date: Monday 12th October 2009

Time: 15:00-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08444737630

Pin: 70503011

Attending

Manchester: Steve, Jits, Carole, Franck, George

EBI: Eric, Rodrigo

Apologies

Minuting

Agenda

Actions from the last telcon

Progress report

BBSRC report

Technical meeting

Summary of tasks on Rubyforge

BioCatalogue support review

20 Questions analysis

Actions from Previous Meeting

Jits: CLA proposal based on the Taverna one. ongoing

Eric: talk to Francois (the french team) about their service monitoring improvements. ongoing

ALL: add your Biocatalogue outreach on the wiki. ongoing

Franck: plan for focus group. ongoing

Rodrigo: identify group at the EBI which could provide us with feedback about the BioCatalogue. completed

Minutes

Steve highlighted the EDAM ontology from embrace. The BioCatalogue can use that. Jon from the EMBRACE group will be in Manchester for the BioCatalogue annotation jamboree.

Eric: test script up and running. has some issues with library versions; which library to select for a specific language? Soaplab team will update their test script to work with the latest library.

Jits: Enhanced search performance. Working on the API

Franck: writing annotation best practice. Sent invitation for the BioCatalogue annotation jamboree.

New actions

Franck: Send around who is doing what for the BBSRC report

Eric/Jits: to talk about script written by Jits for the Embrace import

Upcoming Meetings

AOB

BioCatalogue annotation model meeting 14/10/09

BBSRC report due 01/11/09

The BioCatalogue annotation jamboree 29/11/09

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Sept 28 2009

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Oct 19 2009

The BioCatalogue team has released his first public beta. The BioCatalogue beta has the following features:

BioCatalogue beta....

supports user registration and user profiles for both regular users and service providers.

Supports registration for SOAP, REST and soaplab services.

Handles service discovery by keywords or browsing the latest services submitted; filtering of search result by category, provider, tags and controlled vocabulary.

Supports annotation of services by tags, user comments(powered by Disqus) and text description. Annotated services or their parts (operations, inputs, outputs etc) are searchable.

Ability for users to provide many more types of annotations (like examples, name aliases and so on).

Harvests all annotations and services from Feta.

Exposes an OpenSearch description document.

At-a-glance counts of annotations on services (grouped by provider, user and other registries).

To Get Involved

We are looking for early adopters and testers of the BioCatalogue pilot. You can be a service provider, a developer, a bioinformatician or just interested.

Join our mailing list:
BioCatalogue-Friends Mailing List

Still to come ...

Support for DAS services registration

Integration with myExperiment: on the one hand services from BioCatalogue will be displayed in myExperiment so users of myExperiment can browse them. On the other hand services within workflows in myExperiment will reference the appropriate services in BioCatalogue so users can click through to the information in BioCatalogue.

Integration to Taverna: users will be able to import Web Services and annotations to and from BioCatalogue and Taverna.

Public APIs: RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue.

myBioCatalogue: setup your private BioCatalogue for your project or organisation

For the list of complete features The Roadmap

1st BioCatalogue Strategy Advisory Board meeting

Date: 20th March 2009

Location: University of Manchester

Attending: Carole Goble, Jiten Bhagat, Steve Pettifer, Franck Tanoh, Rodrigo Lopez, Thomas Laurent, Eric Nzuobontane, Chris Rawlings, Anil Wipat, Jo Dicks, Steve Kemp, Antoine H.C. van Kampen, Holger Lausen, Terry Payne

Apologies: Robert Stevens, Mark Wilkinson, Robert Gill, Katy Wolstencroft

Agenda

Presentation of the BioCatalogue project (Carole Goble)

Presentation of the Seekda project (Holger Lausen)

Demonstration of the BioCatalogue private release (Jiten Bhagat, Eric Nzuobontane)

Discussion about current state of the project as well as about its future development

1. Presentation of the BioCatalogue project

BioCatalogue presentation

2. Presentation of the Seekda project

Seekda presentation

3. Demonstration of the BioCatalogue private release

BioCatalogue private release

4. Discussion

The Project

SAB asked “What is the main criteria from the BBSRC for evaluation of this program ?”

Answer: Does anybody use it? How much content? Is it crucial to the community? Significant coverage of the field.

Search

Search terms matched to ontologies, allowing for richer searches.

Thesaurus based search term expansion and presentation of results

BioCatalogue, searchable by Google and EBI search engine.

BioCatalogue to use standard tools for search expansion.

Have a look at the clustering engine carrot2 to enhance the search results returned by SOLR.

Have a look at COHSE to get broader terms and narrower terms.

Browsing

Facetted browsing: classification of services based on domain e.g. proteomic, genomic, metabolomic…etc.

Sourcing from ontology; myGrid ontology may not be enough to annotate all services. We need to source from other ontology as well.

Registration

At registration point ask users/providers to accept terms/conditions; we need advice on that issue e.g. from the business school here in Manchester. We should also ask if the submitter is the provider/owner of the service (how do we do service ownership management ?).

Feedback loop to users and service providers need to be more explicit.

We should ask if submitter of a Web Service is also the owner and ask for the type of notifications wanted.

Annotation

Possibility to use other ontology as well

What a provider gets from providing more metadata.

Make sure we don’t mislead people about services having a lot of metadata but with a bad quality service.

Quality of service

Need to separate subjective rating from objective rating. We should be careful with rating not to offend providers.

Speed of a service difficult to measure and very subjective.

Feedback to provider is an important aspect of the monitoring piece.

“Did it do what I want it to do?”

“Did it do what it said it would do?”

We need to separate out machine vs human AND subjective vs objective measurements

Social networking

We need to be careful not to appear to support any comment post to the BioCatalogue (write disclaimer).

Provide service providers clear paths and opportunities to respond to negative comments.

Suggestion: Multiple comment threads (using DISQUS) to be able to separate general comments from technical issues with a Web Service.

We probably shouldn’t allow anonymous comments.

Provide a “did you find this comment useful”.

Provide a “did you find Web Service you were looking for” for both anonymous and registered users.

Testing

Test script is an example of how to run a service

Tests are a valuable information for users but also an important feedback for service providers (test that their service is working and reachable by the outside world)

Metrics

How many times a Web Service has been seen/visited

We could check how e-commerce websites handles ranking (in literature, with business school…)

Launch strategy

BioCuration/BioIT - silent launch (open up the beta site)

ISMB/ECCB in July, the real launch target. A poster has already been submitted and a demo will be subitted as well (Taverna integration will be ready by then).

We can investigate using Google ads but very VERY expensive.

Mailing lists to advertise the launch on ?

Press releases: talk to journal/publisher about BioCatalogue

Newsletters BBSRC

Students and teaching – Anil’s help

EU networks

Sponsorship of activities

Long term recognition of BioCatalogue

BioCatalogue, the place where publishers such as NAR point their submitters to register web services.

BioCatalogue the number one web service registry for life science

Term of reference SAB

A quarterly small report to send to the SAB team.

Meeting once a year.

Create a SAB mailing list for contact

Action

Franck, submit ISMB demo abstract by 20th April

Carole to talk at the BioIT meeting about our policy

All, Holger invitation for a meeting between the BioCatalogue team and service finder team

Rodrigo: DDBJ, NCBI – ownership and diplomacy

Franck: Sourcing from ontology to be added to the task list

Jits: Create a mailing list for the SAB team

Curation roadmap

Content curation is key to the BioCatalogue. That’s why the BioCatalogue team is working hard to improve the quality and the quantity of annotations in the BioCatalogue. The team will address both technical and social aspects of curation.

The technical aspect should allow users to find the services to annotate and the tool to use. It should also allow the BioCatalogue to automatically import annotations from different sources.

The social aspect aims to encourage members of the BioCatalogue to annotate services.

Technical aspect

UI improvement: Improve the way service operations are displayed in the BioCatalogue [January-March 2010]

Bulk curation tools: spreadsheet like tools [January-March 2010]

Curator reports: to keep curators up to date of the content

Annotation status: has all parts of the service been annotated? How many of them have been annotated? revisit bronze-silver-gold-platinum model.

Write APIs: possibility to import annotation through the BioCatalogue APIs

Service ranking and filtering based on annotation

Screen scraping: bespoke scripts to extract service description from web sites

Who is who? Curator vs casual annotator. Curators will have a stamp next to their name in the catalogue.

Service versioning: same services or similar services will be grouped together. If one is annotated we can derive the annotation of the others.

Social aspect

Outreach: presentation, training and demo of the BioCatalogue

White paper: annotation guidelines

Jamboree: organise a number of annotation jamborees

If you have any suggestions or ideas about how we can improve annotation of web services in the BioCatalogue, please contact us: contact(at)biocatalogue.org